Guide to the Benjamin and Julia Stockton Rush Papers, 1766-1845 and undated RL.11044
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Benjamin and Julia Stockton Rush papers
1766-1845 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
RL.11044
0.8 Linear Feet 3 boxes, 2 volumes
The Benjamin and Julia Stockton Rush papers include letters, writings, financial records, a few legal documents and one educational record. Benjamin Rush's personal and professional outgoing letters, with some incoming letters, cover a wide variety of topics, but focus primarily on medical concerns, particularly the 1793 and other yellow fever epidemics in Philadelphia, as well as mental illness and its treatment, and the medical department of the Continental Army. There are a few letters from others to Julia Stockton Rush that seek to continue ties with her and the Rush family or offer condolences following Benjamin's death. Collection also contains a medical case book and a fragment of an essay or lecture written by Benjamin Rush, along with his travel diary for a trip to meet with the Board of Trustees for Dickinson College in 178[4]; other writings include Julia Rush's devotional journal and exercise book. The financial records include a few statements and receipts, but primarily contain two account books, one maintained by Benjamin Rush, the other by Rush with his wife. These account books provide a complete picture of the family finances from the period before the couple married, almost to Julia's death. Legal documents include a sworn statement and a land patent, and there is an educational record for one of Rush's students.
Arrangement
Arranged into the following series: Letters, Writings, Financial Records, and Legal Documents and Educational Records.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Collection Overview
The Benjamin and Julia Stockton Rush papers include letters, writings, financial records, a few legal documents and one educational record.
Benjamin Rush's personal and professional outgoing letters, with some incoming letters, cover a wide variety of topics, but focus primarily on medical concerns, particularly the 1793 and other yellow fever epidemics in Philadelphia, as well as mental illness and its treatment, and the medical department of the Continental Army.
There are a few letters from others to Julia Stockton Rush that seek to continue ties with her and the Rush family or offer condolences following Benjamin's death. Collection also contains a medical case book and a fragment of an essay or lecture written by Benjamin Rush, along with his travel diary for a trip to meet with the Board of Trustees for Dickinson College in 178[4]; other writings include Julia Rush's devotional journal and exercise book.
The financial records include a few statements and receipts, but primarily contain two account books, one maintained by Benjamin Rush, the other by Rush with his wife. These account books provide a complete picture of the family finances from the period before the couple married, almost to Julia's death.
Legal documents include a sworn statement and a land patent, and there is an educational record for one of Rush's students.
Biographical Note
Benjamin Rush was a physician, politician, social reformer, educator and humanitarian, as well as the founder of Dickinson College in Carlisle, Pennsylvania. He married Julia Stockton in 1776.
Benjamin Rush
1746 January 4 Born, in Byberry Township, Pa.
1760 Graduated with A. B., College of New Jersey (Princeton)
1761-1766 Medical apprenticeship, College of Philadelphia medical department
1768 Completed medical degree, University of Edinburgh
1769 Began medical practice in Philadelphia Appointed Professor of Chemistry in College of Philadelphia's medical department
1776 Took his seat in Second Continental Congress
1776 August 2 Signed Declaration of Independence
1777 April Commissioned Surgeon General of Middle Department of the Continental Army
1778 Resigned from the Army Became lecturer at University of the State of Pennsylvania
1783 Helped found Dickinson College in Carlisle, Pa.
1784-1813 Surgeon at Pennsylvania Hospital, with responsibility for psychiatric ward
1797-1813 Treasurer of the U.S. Mint
1813 Died
Julia Stockton Rush
1759 Born, at "Morven" family estate near Princeton, N.J.
1776 Married Benjamin Rush; the couple went on to have 13 children
1848 Died at their county property, "Sydenham" (now 15th Street and Columbus Ave, Philadelphia)
Related Materials
Sarah Eve diary, 1772-1773. Eve was the daughter of ship captain and merchant Oswell Eve, and the fiancee of Benjamin Rush until her death on 4 Dec. 1774, three weeks before the date set for their marriage.
Physicians -- Records and correspondence.; Medicine -- Study and teaching -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Mental illness -- Treatment -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Yellow Fever -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Medical care; United States -- Politics and government -- 1775-1783; Diaries; Rush, Julia Stockton; Dickinson College
- Letters, 1777-1824; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The majority of the 136 letters in the series were composed by Benjamin Rush, and letters he wrote to Julia during the 1793 yellow fever epidemic in Philadelphia form a substantial part of the series. Main topics in the letters include Rush family matters, medical treatments for a wide variety of medical issues, American politics, and the country's relations with European nations. Other topics include mental illness and its treatment, the medical department in the Continental Army, the impact of epidemics upon commerce internationally, reading habits, parenting, and capital punishment.
  Among the prominent correspondents who wrote one or more personal or professional letters to Rush or his wife are Abigail Adams, John Quincy Adams, Thomas Jefferson, James Madison, Thomas Paine, and George Washington. Letters from others to Julia Rush seek to continue ties with her and the Rush family, and offer condolences following Benjamin's death. Included are several manuscript copies Benjamin Rush made of individual letters he penned.
  - Abigail Adams (n.p.) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Philadelphia), 1813 July 7; Adams, Abigail, 1744-1818; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Josiah Charles Trent Collection, 1956
    Adams sends her condolences to Rush, and confides her own concern about her daughter's struggles with breast cancer.
    Breast -- Cancer; Breast Neoplasms; Rush, Julia Stockton
  - John Quincy Adams (St. Petersburg, Russia) letter to Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia), 1811 January 11; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Adams writes regarding his presenting a copy of Rush's "Medical Inquiries and Observations" to the Emperor of Russia, who is sending Rush a ring in thanks.
    Medicine -- Russia -- History -- 19th century; Education, Medical -- History -- Russia (Pre-1917); History of Medicine -- Russia (Pre-1917); Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - John Dickinson (n. p.) letter to Benjamin Rush (n. p.), 1784 August 13; Dickinson, John, 1732-1808; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Dickinson writes that he has read with pleasure Rush's essay on female education. He requests Rush's help with another project, "to prepare the public Mind for receiving…the proceedings of the Convention."
    Women -- Education -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - John Dickinson (Kent [England]) letter to Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia), 1798 April 2; Dickinson, John, 1732-1808; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Dickinson writes that he has purchased and perused all the doctor's works and requests his help in diagnosing and treating a child that is in excruciating pain.
    Pediatrics -- 18th century; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - John Dickinson (n. p.) note to Benjamin Rush (n. p.), 1804; Dickinson, John, 1732-1808; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 22 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    In a note, Dickinson comments on their health, and on the 4th part of an unidentified manuscript.
    Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Horatio Gates (New York) letter to Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia), 1803 August 8; Gates, Horatio, 1728-1806; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gates indicates that he will try the remedies Rush suggested. He believes that England is likely to become a despotism, and notes that there is a rumor in New York City that England will defeat America's treaty with France regarding Louisiana.
    Medicine -- Formulae, receipts, prescriptions; Treaty of Paris (1803); Despotism -- Great Britain; Louisiana Purchase; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Nathanael Greene (n. p.) letter to Benjamin Rush (n. p.), 1777 May 3; Greene, Nathanael, 1742-1786; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Greene writes of his support for Rush's recommendations regarding best methods for preserving the health of the Army. He suggests they print a pamphlet on the topic, to make adoption of the recommendations more likely. He comments on Congress' regulation of hospitals.
    United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Medical care; Military hospitals -- United States; Medicine, Military -- United States -- History -- 18th century; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Richard Henderson (Leesburg [Va.]) letter to Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia), 1810 June 11; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 30 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    1-page transcript available
    Henderson replies to Rush's letter regarding the debts of a Mr. Carter, assuring Rush that he is in error, all costs for the preparation of coffin and grave have been paid.
    Death -- Social aspects -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Burial -- Social aspects -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Mary Hosack (New York) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Philadelphia), 1811 June 26; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 7)
    2-page transcript available
    Mary Hosack writes regarding family health matters, her husband's connections, and the Rush's possible visit to New York.
    Families -- Health and hygiene -- United States; Rush, Julia Stockton
  - David Hosack (n. p.) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Philadelphia), 1824 May 4; Hosack, David, 1769-1835; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 7)
    David Hosack acknowledges Julia Rush's letter and states that he has sent a keepsake in memory of his wife. He requests that she consider a visit to them.
    Rush, Julia Stockton
  - Thomas Jefferson (Washington [D.C.]) letter to Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia), 1801 December 20; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Jefferson discusses vaccinations in Philadelphia, the impact of his sending a message rather than making a speech at the opening of Congress, the political implications of suppressing taxes, and his desire to live a long, healthy, and useful life.
    Vaccination -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Tax collection -- United States -- History; Aging; United States -- Politics and government -- 1801-1809; Older people -- Psychology; Older people -- Health and hygiene; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Thomas Jefferson (Washington [D.C.]) letter to Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia), 1808 January 3; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Jefferson notes that he has appointed Dr. Waterhouse to the Marine hospital in Boston, in return for his introducing vaccinations to the country, and describes the political fallout from the appointment. He plans to send his 15-year-old grandson to be with Rush in the Fall. He mentions Dr. Rose, and the impact on an embargo on relations with Europe.
    United States -- Politics and government -- 1801-1809; Vaccination -- United States -- History -- 19th century; United States -- Foreign relations -- Europe -- 19th century; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; Waterhouse, Benjamin, 1754-1846
  - James McHenry (York Island, Fort Washington) letter to Benjamin Rush (n. p.), 1776 November 2; McHenry, James, 1753-1816; 2 Leaves; 8 pages; 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 10)
    McHenry details reforms required within the Army's medical department and makes recommendations for restructuring of general and regimental hospitals, controlling fraud in the commissaries, increasing the numbers of nurses and surgeons, and improving the distribution of medicine.
  - James Madison (Washington [D.C.]) letter to Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia), 1801 June 28; Madison, James, 1751-1836; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Madison writes regarding quarantine laws in Europe and their impact on commerce with the United States, with reference to yellow fever in particular.
    International trade; Epidemics; Communicable diseases; Yellow Fever; Disease Transmission, Infectious -- History; Communicable Disease Control -- History; Quarantine -- History; Yellow Fever -- History; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Thomas Paine (n. p.) letter to Benjamin Rush (n. p.), 1785 December 30; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Paine recommends a candidate for the midwifery position on the faculty at the University of Pennsylvania.
    University of Pennsylvania -- Faculty; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Felix Pascalis Ouvriere (New York) letter to Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia), 1812 December 22; Pascalis Ouviere, Felix, 1762-1833; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Pascalis acknowledges receipt of two essays. He states that he has not yet had the opportunity to read Dr. Rush's treatise on the diseases of the mind, but that he plans to write a review of it.
    Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813 -- Medical inquiries and observations upon the diseases of the mind
  - Felix Pascalis Ouvriere (New York) letter to Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia), 1813 March 1; Pascalis Ouviere, Felix, 1762-1833; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Pascalis writes with citations regarding Rush's "Tranquilizer arm-chair" designed for maniacs, as well as details of publishing translations and copyright issues.
    Publishers and publishing -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Timothy Pickering (Philadelphia) letter to Benjamin Rush (n. p.), 1799 September 23; Pickering, Timothy, 1745-1829; 3 Leaves; 6 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Pickering notes that he sent Yellow Fever medicine developed by Dr. Conrad G. Bölke to the Board of Health, but is only now sending along copies of his letters from Bölke and the United States consul at Hamburg, Joseph Pitcairn, with instructions regarding the medicine's use.
    Yellow fever -- Treatment; Yellow Fever -- therapy; Yellow fever -- 18th century; Yellow Fever -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Yellow Fever -- Epidemiology -- Pennsylvania; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Timothy Pickering (Washington [D.C.]) letter to Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia), 1804 November 17; Pickering, Timothy, 1745-1829; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Pickering writes regarding his plans for caring for his mentally disturbed son, William, thanking Dr. Rush for his advice. In a postscript, he asks Rush if he should talk to his son about his derangement when he is rational in order to have his cooperation in effecting a cure.
    Mental illness -- Treatment -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Mentally ill -- Treatment -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Timothy Pickering (Salem [Mass.]) letter to Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia), 1807 July 5; Pickering, Timothy, 1745-1829; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Pickering details how the family is no longer able to care for William. He has decided to send William to Rush's hospital in Philadelphia, where he will not be able to escape and might recover. He adds that another son, George, is potentially manifesting the same symptoms as William.
    Mental illness -- Treatment -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Mentally ill -- Commitment and detention -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Mentally ill -- Treatment -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Timothy Pickering (Washington [D.C.]) letter to Benjamin Rush (n. p.), 1808 November 17; Pickering, Timothy, 1745-1829; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Pickering describes symptoms for which he would like Rush's treatment advice. Includes Rush's own notes regarding two prescriptions he advised.
    Medicine -- Practice -- United States -- 19th century; Medicine -- Formulae, receipts, prescriptions; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to unidentified, 1777 April 2; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 4 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush congratulates the unnamed recipient on his recent appointment in the army, and makes note of the support of France and Spain in America's revolutionary cause, along with other Mediterranean countries. He mentions that the army expects to check any advance of General Howe into Philadelphia, whose appearance would cause a panic. He notes that his opposition to Pennsylvania's current government has cost him his seat in Congress, but that he had planned to join the army in any case.
    United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; United States -- Foreign relations -- France; United States -- Foreign relations -- Spain; United States -- Foreign relations -- Europe; Howe, William Howe, Viscount, 1729-1814
  - Benjamin Rush (n.p.) letter to unidentified, 1777 Autumn; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush discusses his appointment to the Army, the support of doctors Shippen and Brower for that appointment, his concerns about the medical system and the numbers of deaths the army has experienced, dispatches that have arrived from France, and that John Adams is on his way there.
    United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Medical care; Medicine, Military -- United States -- History -- 18th century; United States -- History -- 18th Century; Shippen, William, 1712-1801
  - Benjamin Rush (Princetown) letter to unidentified, 1778 April 20-21; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 2 Leaves; 8 pages; 22 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush states that he is never indifferent to any thing relating to America, and that the basis for America's freedom is broad, but is in danger from a tedious and expensive war, and from "the ignorance, indolence, and avarice of too many of our Whigs." He follows with questions regarding the country's finances, then notes that he has ordered a court-martial of Dr. Shippen, for whom he will serve as prosecutor. A postscript discusses two bills before Congress.
    United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Economic aspects; United States -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Shippen, William, 1712-1801
  - Benjamin Rush (Princetown) letter to James McHenry (n. p.), 1778 May 17; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 22 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush recommends Dr. James Finley to McHenry, and requests that he visit Finley's patients with him. He adds that he is forced into a military retirement by Dr. Shippen's friends, but takes pleasure in McHenry's service. Finally, he comments on the alliance with France.
    United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Medical care; Medicine, Military -- United States -- History -- 18th century; United States -- Foreign relations -- France; McHenry, James, 1753-1816.; Shippen, William, 1712-1801
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Rushhill), 1779 July 30; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush relays his plans to visit Julia. A postscript instructs her how to protect herself and the babies from contracting a fever.
    Fever -- Early works to 1800; Rush, Julia Stockton
  - Benjamin Rush (Morristown, NJ) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Philadelphia), 1780 March 17; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush writes regarding the health of Julia's uncle's family, one of whom is suffering from a stomach disorder. He also notes that Julia's father's health is deteriorating. Her father will accompany him upon his return, to be placed under another physician's care. He requests that Julia have his assistants call upon the parents of children Rush inoculated before his departure, with instructions for their care. He describes the trial of a Dr. Shippen. He mentions that the letter was written in company, in General Green[e?]'s office.
    Medicine -- Practice -- United States -- 18th century; Vaccination -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 18th Century; Rush, Julia Stockton; Shippen, William, 1712-1801
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1781 March 12; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 34 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush writes regarding shipment arrangements for materials Julia has requested. He notes that a new tenant has taken possession of their farm. He inquires regarding Julia's health, they comments on the difficulty of separation from her. Rush's signature has been removed from the letter.
    Man-woman relationships -- 18th century; Rush, Julia Stockton
  - Benjamin Rush (n.p.) note to Librarian of the Pensyla. Lib[rary] (n.p.), 1781 April 20; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Autograph collections of Dr. Max Thorek; Gift of Josiah Charles Trent Collection, 1956
    Note by Rush requesting that no more books be lent to Mr. Dick on Dr. Rush's account, but permitting the bearer of the note to borrow any books required.
    Books and reading -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 18th century
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to [General Nathanael Greene, n.p.], 1782 April 15; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 4 pages; 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush congratulates Greene on his successes in North Carolina, then recommends that he move from Rhode Island to South Carolina, which is more active in manners and government and would suit him better. He then comments upon the country's need for Confederation and for a national character built upon something more than resentment of Great Britain.
    United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Nationalism -- United States -- History -- 18th century; Greene, Nathanael, 1742-1786
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Jacob Read (n. p.), 1782 April 23; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rush rejoices in Read's recovery and safe return to South Carolina and sends greetings to Read's family. He outlines family news, including that Julia has given birth to another girl and Mrs. Boudinott has spent the winter. He adds that the women humanize their friend, Dr. Ramsay, in preparation for his finding a wife.
    Read, Jacob, 1752-1816; Rush family
  - Rush, Benjamin (n.p.) letter to [John Bubenheim Bayard], 1784 June 25; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 2 Leaves; 3 pages; 34 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)